Dr. Panpan Cai

□ cindycia.github.io
□ cindycia.github.io

I am a roboticist. I have been conducting active research in decision making under uncertainty, robot learning, and integrating them to solve complex real-world robotics problems. My research vision is to enable robots to operate efficiently in large-scale, dynamic, and uncertain environments like human, and accomplish challenging tasks.

Education

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

Doctor of Philosophy

2011.8-2016.7

Research on robotic motion planning, collision detection, and GPU computing.

Zhejiang University

Hangzhou, China

Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics (specialized on Information and Computing Science)

Top student selected into the ChuKoChen Honors College

2007.8-2011.6

Trained on Mathematics, scientific computing, and Computer Aided Geometric Design (CAGD).

Professional Experience

Qing Yuan Research Institute, Shanghai Jiao Tong University

China

Associate professor

2022-now

- o Started my own research group on robot intelligence;
- o Research scope: robot learning, robot decision making, reinforcement learning, integrating planning and learning;
- o Application domains: autonomous driving and home service robots.

Department of Computer Science, National University of Singapore

Singapore

Senior postdoctoral research fellow

2021-2022

- o Conduct independent research and lead research projects on integrating planning with reinforcement learning;
- Publish in top robotics conferences and journals, including T-RO, RAL, RSS, and ICRA;
- o Mentored an undergraduate student for an award-winning final year project, as well as master students and research interns for independent research;
- o Organized an international workshop (main organizer) under a top robotics conference, RSS 2021;
- o Taught two lectures in a graduate-level robotics class on POMDP planning, robot systems, and autonomous driving.

Department of Computer Science, National University of Singapore

Singapore

Postdoctoral research fellow

2017-2020

- o Conduct independent research and lead research projects on decision making under uncertainty, integrating planning and learning, and autonomous driving in crowded environments;
- o Publish in top robotics conferences and journals, including IJRR, RAL, RSS, ICRA, and IROS;
- o Mentored PhD, undergraduate, and intern students for independent research;
- o Taught a lecture in a graduate-level robotics class on sampling-based motion planning.

School of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, Nanyang Technological University PhD student

Singapore 2011-2016

Conduct independent research on parallel collision detection and motion planning in large-scale industrial environments;

- o Publish in tier-one journals on industrial applications of robotics and automation;
- Close collaboration with a listed lifting service company;
- o Published a patent on intelligent crane-lifting systems.
- o Taught an undergraduate-level lab project.

Publications

Citation: 533 (queried at 05.06.2023)

H-index: 10 i10-index: 10

Peer-reviewed journal papers:

- o P. Cai and D. Hsu. Closing the Planning-Learning Loop with Application to Autonomous Driving in a Crowd. IEEE Transactions on Robotics (T-RO), 2023, DOI:10.1109/TRO.2022.3210767.
- o Y. Luo*, P. Cai* (co-first author, corresponding author), D. Hsu, and WS Lee. GAMMA: A General Agent Motion Model for Autonomous Driving. IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL), 2022, DOI:10.1109/LRA.2022.3144501.

- o P. Cai, Y. Luo, D. Hsu, and W.S. Lee. HyP-DESPOT: A Hybrid Parallel Algorithm for Online Planning under Uncertainty. *International Journal of Robotics Research (IJRR)*, 2021, DOI:10.1177/0278364920937074.
- Y. Luo, <u>P. Cai</u>, A. Bera, D. Hsu, W.S. Lee, and D. Manocha. PORCA: Modeling and planning for autonomous driving among many pedestrians. *IEEE Robotics Automation Letters (RAL)*, 2018, DOI:10.1109/LRA.2018.2852793.
- o <u>P. Cai</u>, Y. Cai, I. Chandrasekaran, and J. Zheng "Automatic Path Planning for Dual-Crane Lifting in Complex Environments Using a Prioritized Multi-objective PGA", *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics (TII)*, 2017, DOI:10.1109/TII.2017.2715835.
- o <u>P. Cai</u>, Y. Cai, I. Chandrasekaran, and J. Zheng. "Parallel GA based automatic crane lifting path planning in complex environments", *Automation in Construction (AIC)*, 2016, DOI:10.1016/J.AUTCON.2015.09.007.

Peer-reviewed conference papers:

- o M. H. Danesh, P. Cai (corresponding author), D.Hsu. LEADER: Learning Attention over Driving Behaviors for Planning under Uncertainty. *Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)* (Best paper finalist), Dec 2022, PMLR 205:199-211.
- Y. Lee and P. Cai, and D. Hsu. MAGIC: Learning Macro-Actions for Online POMDP Planning using Generator-Critic. *Robotics: Science & Systems (RSS)*, July 2021, DOI:10.15607/RSS.2021.XVII.041.
- P. Cai* (co-first author), Y. Lee*, Y. Luo, D. Hsu. SUMMIT: A Simulator for Urban Driving in Massive Mixed Traffic.
 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), June 2020, DOI:10.1109/ICRA40945.2020.9197228.
- P. Cai, Y. Luo, A. Saxena, D. Hsu, W.S. Lee. LeTS-Drive: Driving in a Crowd by Learning from Tree Search. Robotics: Science & Systems (RSS), June 2019, DOI:10.15607/RSS.2019.XV.018.
- o M. Meghjani, Y. Luo, Q.H. Ho, <u>P. Cai</u>, S. Verma, D. Rus, D. Hsu. Context and Intention Aware Planning for Urban Driving. *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Nov. 2019, DOI:10.1109/IROS40897.2019. 8967873.
- o P. Cai, Y. Luo, D. Hsu, and W.S. Lee. HyP-DESPOT: A Hybrid Parallel Algorithm for Online Planning under Uncertainty. *Robotics: Science & Systems (RSS)*, June 2018, DOI:10.15607/RSS.2018.XIV.004.
- o L. Huang, Y. Zhang, J. Zheng, <u>P. Cai</u>, S. Dutta, Y. Yue, N. Thalmann and Y. Cai. Point cloud based path planning for tower crane lifting. Computer Graphics International Conference (CGI), June 2018, DOI:10.1145/3208159.3208186.
- o <u>P. Cai</u>, Y. Cai, I. Chandrasekaran, and J. Zheng, "A GPU-enabled parallel genetic algorithm for path planning", 2013 Symposium on GPU Computing and Applications (Best Paper), Oct 2013, DOI:10.1007/978-981-287-134-3_1.

Book chapters:

- o <u>P. Cai</u>, I. Chandrasekaran, Y. Cai, Y. Chen, and X. Wu. Simulation-enabled vocational training for heavy crane operations. In *Simulation and Serious Games for Education* (pp. 47-59), 2017, DOI: 10.1007/978-981-10-0861-0_4.
- o P. Cai, C. Indhumathi, Y. Cai, J. Zheng, Y. Gong, T. Lim, and P. Wong. Collision detection using axis aligned bounding boxes. In *Simulations, Serious Games and Their Applications* (pp. 1-14), 2014, DOI:10.1007/978-981-4560-32-0_1.

Patent

o Y. Cai, P. Cai, C. Indhumathi, J. Zheng, N. M. Thalmann, P. Wong, T. S. Lim and Y. Gong, PEC Ltd and Nanyang Technological University. Method and system for intelligent crane lifting. WIPO (PCT), 2015, WO2015053711A1.

Professional Services

Program and Organization Committees:

- o Associate Editor, IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2023.
- o Program committee member, International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS), 2022.
- o Main organizer, RSS 2021 workshop on Integrating Planning and Learning.
- o Organization committee member, RSS Pioneers Workshop, 2021.
- o Program committee member, Robotics: Science & Systems (RSS), 2020.
- o Program committee member, Conference on Robot Learning (CORL), 2019.
- o Organization committee member, CS research week 2019, School of Computing, NUS.

Paper Review:

- o International Journal of Robotics Research (IJRR)
- o IEEE Transactions on Robotics (T-RO)
- Robotics: Science & Systems (RSS)
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)
- Autonomous Robots (AURO)
- o IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)
- International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)
- American Control Conference (ACC)

o International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)

Teaching & Mentoring

Lecturing:

- o Co-lecturing, Module CS3317 "Artificial Intelligence", Autumn Semester, 2022/2023, SJTU.
 - Undergraduate-level course, covering more than 50 students.
- o Co-lecturing, Module CS4278/CS5478 "Intelligent Robots: Algorithms and Systems", Semester 1&2, 2021/2022, NUS.
 - Graduate-level course, covering more than 100 students.
 - Delivered Lecture 11 "POMDP planning."
 - Delivered Lecture 12 "Robot systems."
- o Co-lecturing, Module CS6244 "Robot Motion Planning & Control", Semester 1, 2017/2018, Lecture 3, NUS.
 - Graduate-level course, covering 20-30 students.
 - Delivered Lecture 3 "Sampling-based motion planning."
- o Teaching assistance, Project P3.6 "Vibration Testing of Multiple DOF Systems" for AY 2015/16, S1 & S2, NTU.
 - Undergraduate-level class, covering 12 students.
 - Delivered a series of short lectures on the theory of mechanical vibration and guided lab experiments.

Mentoring

- o Supervising PhD students and master students at Shanghai Jiao Tong University.
- o Co-supervising Mr. Yunfan Lu for his master research. He is now a Senior Robotics Software Engineer at Dyson.
- o Supervising Mr. Mohamad Danesh for his research internship. He is now a research engineer at Ivy.
- o Co-supervised Mr. Yiyuan Lee for his Final Year Project; He is now a PhD candidate at Rice University.
- o Supervised Ms. Shuyuan Jin for her Final Year Project. She is now a Software Engineer at Facebook.
- o Co-supervised Dr. Yuanfu Luo for his PhD research. He is now an algorithm engineer at Da-Jiang Innovations.
- o Supervised Mr. Arthur Wandzel for his research internship. He is now the co-founder of JAMM, an Al startup.
- o Supervised Mr. Aseem Saxena for his research internship. He is now a master student at Oregon State University.

Research Talks

- o Invited talk at Kuwa Robot. "How does a robot drive better than us?", May 2023.
- o Invited talk at SenseTime, an international AI company. "How does a robot drive better than us?", Aug 2022.
- o Invited talk at the Computer Science Department at <u>Brown University</u>. "How does a robot drive better than us?", Aug 2020.
- Al lunch talk at the School of Computing, <u>National University of Singapore</u>. "Hybrid intelligence of robots: modeling, decision making, and learning", Oct 2019.
- o Invited talk at ISEE AI, an MIT startup on autonomous driving. "How can a robot drive better than us?", Nov 2019.
- Invited talk at the School of Mathematical Sciences, <u>Zhejiang University</u>. "Planning under uncertainty in robotics: theory to practice, and serial to parallel", May 2018.

References

o Dr. David Hsu (IEEE Fellow).

Provost's Chair Professor. Department of Computer Science. National University of Singapore.

Relationship: Postdoc supervisor. Email: dyhsu@comp.nus.edu.sg

Phone: +65 6825 4200 o Dr. Wee Sun Lee.

Professor, Head of Department. Department of Computer Science. National University of Singapore.

Relationship: close collaborator. Email: leews@comp.nus.edu.sg Phone: +65 6516 4526

+05 0510 4

o Dr. Yiyu Cai.

Associate professor. School of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering. Nanyang Technological University.

Relationship: PhD supervisor. Email: MYYCai@ntu.edu.sg Phone: +65 6790 5941